Guide to the Grimes Family Films and Other Materials AIA.040
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grimes Family Films and Other Materials
1896-1999
1947-1958
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Grimes, Paddy, 1890-1978
Grimes, Claire
Grimes, John
AIA.040
2 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons
The Grimes Family is an Irish American family based in the greater New York City area perhaps best known for their ownership of the Irish Echo newspaper from 1955 until 2011. Through its domestic and international social, political, sporting, and entertainment coverage, the Irish Echo served as a channel of communication and source of documentation for the Irish American community. This collection consists of home movies, photographs, publications, ephemera, and other materials created and collected by members of the Grimes Family, including Paddy, John, and Claire. The majority of the collection is comprised of some of the Grimes' home movies, documenting family life as well as various Irish American social functions in the greater New York City area during the 1950s. Some of the more prominent subjects of these films include sporting events, St. Patrick's Day parades, and United Irish Counties Association Feiseanna at Fordham University.
Box 1
Box 2
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irish Echo Photographs (AIA 045)
Archives of Irish American United Irish Counties Association Collection (AIA 056)
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Biographical Note
The Grimes Family is an Irish American family based in the greater New York City area perhaps best known for their ownership of the Irish Echo newspaper from 1955 until 2011. Patrick J. (Paddy) Grimes, a native of Co. Offaly, purchased the newspaper in 1955 in an attempt to promote the family's travel agency, Grimes Travel Agency. Through its domestic and international social, political, sporting, and entertainment coverage, the Irish Echo served as a channel of communication and source of documentation for the Irish American community. For example, the paper produced brochures and journals for the various county societies and other social organizations in the 1950s and 1960s. Following Paddy's death in 1978, his son John became the paper's editor and publisher until his death in 1987, after which his wife Claire assumed the roles.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of home movies, photographs, publications, ephemera, and other materials created and collected by members of the Grimes Family, including Paddy, John, and Claire. The majority of the collection is comprised of some of the Grimes' home movies, documenting family life as well as various Irish American social functions in the greater New York City area during the 1950s. Some of the more prominent subjects of these films include sporting events, St. Patrick's Day parades, and United Irish Counties Association Feiseanna at Fordham University.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Prcoedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Films were donated by Claire Grimes in the late 1990s. The accession number associated with this gift is 1997.041. The remainder of the collection was donated by Claire Grimes several years later.
Amateur films; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.); Irish Americans -- Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans -- Social life and customs.; United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.
- P.J. Kerley and Family Leaving for Ireland at Idlewild Airport, 1957; cuid14047 (Item aia40-1, Reel COMP aia40-a)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, Mar 17, 1956; cuid14048 (Item aia40-1, Reel COMP aia40-d)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, 1953; cuid14049 (Item aia40-1, Reel COMP aia40-g)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, Speaking Platforms, 1953; cuid14050 (Item aia40-1, Reel COMP aia40-i)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade and United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1955; cuid14051 (Item aia40-1, Reel COMP aia40-o)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade and Sir Basil Brooke Protest at Idlewild Airport, Mar 17, 1950, Apr 6, 1950; cuid14052 (Item aia40-1, Reel COMP aia40-r)
- Ireland and New York Compilation Reel, circa 1950-1959; cuid14053; 1 film reels 16mm; 2 videocassettes (betacamsp) Transfers of 16mm film (Item aia40-w, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.40_cuid14053)
- Gaelic Teams Disembarking Shannon Airport, Ireland, circa Nov 1954; cuid84 (Item aia40-j)
- Dublin, Ireland, 1955; cuid85 (Item aia40-u)
- Dublin, Ireland, 1955; cuid86 (Item aia40-v)
- Dublin, Ireland (Probably "Flight of the Gaels"), circa 1955; cuid87 (Item aia40-m)
- Paddy Casey Leaving for Ireland at Idlewild Airport, 1958; cuid88 (Item aia40-b)
- Wedding and Gaelic Football Team, circa 1965; cuid89 (Item aia40-n)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, 1956; cuid90 (Item aia40-c)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, Mar 17, 1956; cuid91 (Item aia40-e)
- Pat Grimes Graduation and United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, 1952; cuid92 (Item aia40-f, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid92)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University; Dublin, Ireland, 1952; cuid93 (Item aia40-k, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid93)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University (Includes Football Match), 1952; cuid94 (Item aia40-l, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid94)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1955; cuid95 (Item aia40-h, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid95)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1955; cuid96 (Item aia40-t, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid96)
- United Irish Counties Association Feis at Fordham University, circa 1950-1959; cuid97 (Item aia40-q, Box Digitized Access Files, File aia.040_cuid97)
- P.J. Grimes Film, circa 1955; cuid98 (Item aia40-s)
- Indian Couple Visits Country House, circa 1953; cuid99 (Item aia40-p)
- American Football Newsreel, circa 1947; cuid100 (Item aia40-y)
- New York City St. Patrick's Day Parade, circa 1950-1959; cuid101 (Item aia40-w)
- Ephemera and Photographs, undated; cuid14054 (Box 1)